<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="f-spot" lang="C">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>The F-Spot Manual</title>
		<abstract role="description">
			<para>This is the user manual for F-Spot, a GNOME personal photo manager.</para>
		</abstract>
		<subtitle>This is the user manual for F-Spot, a GNOME personal photo manager.</subtitle>
		<copyright>
			<year>2007</year>
			<holder>Aaron Bockover, Gabriel Burt, Miguel de Icaza, Bengt Thuree</holder>
		</copyright>
		<publisher>
			<publishername>GNOME Documentation Project</publishername>
		</publisher>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Miguel</firstname>
				<surname>de Icaza</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Aaron</firstname>
				<surname>Bockover</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Bengt</firstname>
				<surname>Thuree</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Gabriel</firstname>
				<surname>Burt</surname>
			</author>
			<author role="maintainer">
				<firstname>Stephane</firstname>
				<surname>Delcroix</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<!--<include href="legal.xml" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>-->
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>0.2</revnumber>
				<date>2007-01-17</date>
			</revision>
		 </revhistory>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="organizing">
		<title>Organizing your photos</title>
		
		<sect1 id="import">
			<title>Import</title>

			<para>
				You can import photos from your hard drive or your camera. When you 
				import your photos into F-Spot from your camera, it will always make a 
				copy of them, leaving you free to clear your camera's memory. By default, 
				F-Spot will make a copy of photos imported from your hard drive. Uncheck 
				the <guilabel>Copy</guilabel> option on the import dialog or hold 
				<keycap>Shift</keycap> when dragging photos into F-Spot if you do not 
				wish to copy them from your hard drive.
			</para>

			<para>
				If all the photos you are importing at one time are from a particular event, 
				or have some other characteristic in common, you can create a tag for them 
				so you can later find them with ease. To do this, follow the instructions below 
				to <ulink url="tag">create a new tag</ulink>, then when you are importing 
				them, check the button for <guilabel>Attach Tag</guilabel> and choose the 
				tag you created. 
			</para>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="edit">
			<title>Edit</title>
			
			<para>
				If you double click or press enter on an image, you enter Edit mode, where 
				you can remove red-eye, crop, and adjust brightness and colors.
			</para>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-versions">
				<title>Versions</title>
				
				<para>
					When you edit your photos, a new copy (called a version) is created, 
					so your original is never altered. After your first edit to a photo, subsequent 
					edits will modify the same version. If you want to create mulitple versions 
					of your photo, perhaps with different cropping or coloring, you can do so 
					via the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Create new version</guimenuitem></menuchoice> option.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-adjust-colors">
				<title>Adjust Colors</title>
				
				<para>
					To adjust the brightness, contrast, and colors of a photo, first click the 
					<guibutton>Adjust Photos</guibutton> icon to open the adjustment dialog. 
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-remove-red-eye">
				<title>Remove Red-Eye</title>
				
				<para>
					To remove redeye from a photo, you need to select each individual eye. 
					You may want to zoom in on the image to accurately select the eyes in 
					the photo.
				</para>
				<para>
					To make your selection, click one corner of the rectangle that will be your 
					selection, and drag your mouse to the diagonal corner and release it. You 
					can resize your selection by dragging its edges, and you can move it by 
					clicking in the middle of it and dragging it to where you want it.
				</para>
				<para>
					Once you have selected an eye, you can remove the red from it by clicking 
					the red-eye button beneath the photo. 
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-crop">
				<title>Crop</title>
				
				<para>
					Cropping an image is a great way to improve the quality of a photograph by 
					improving how it is framed. You crop a photo by selecting the part of the photo 
					you want to keep. If you want your photo to be the exact dimensions necessary 
					for a certain print size, you can constrain the kind of selection F-Spot will allow 
					you to draw by choosing the appropriate size from the constraint drop down. 
					See the <xref linkend="edit-remove-red-eye"/> above for details on making 
					a selection on your photo.
				</para>
				<para>
					Once you have made your crop selection, you must click the crop button beneath 
					the image to finalize the crop. If you are working with the original photo, cropping 
					creates a new version your photo.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-describe">
				<title>Describe</title>
				
				<para>
					You can also enter a description of the image by clicking on the text entry box 
					below the image and typing. 
				</para>
				<para>
					Once you have made your crop selection, you must click the crop button beneath 
					the image to finalize the crop. If you are working with the original photo, cropping 
					creates a new version your photo.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="tag">
			<title>Tag</title>
			<para>
				F-Spot enables you to organize and enjoy your photos by associating them 
				with various user-customizable tags. A tag is a merely a label. F-Spot comes 
				with default tags to get you started; you are free to change them and 
				add new ones. For example, if you want to create a tag for specific event, you 
				can create a new tag named after that event under the Events tag.
			</para>
			<para>
				There are many ways to tag photos:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						drag and drop the photo(s) onto the tag
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						drag and drop the tag onto the photo(s)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						via the photo's right-click menu
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						via the Tags and Edit menus
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						by typing them in (press <keycap>t</keycap> to pop up the tag entry bar, 
						enter comma-separated tags) - with tab completion!
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				The first photo you associate with a tag will be used for that tag's icon. 
				You can always edit a tag's name, parent tag, and icon by right clicking 
				on it and choosing <guilabel>Edit tag</guilabel>.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can change a tag's parent by dragging and dropping it where you like. 
				Also, you can edit the name of a tag by selecting it and pressing 
				<keycap>F2</keycap>. Lastly, if you have the tag tree widget focused 
				(e.g. you just clicked on a tag), you can start typing the name of a tag, and 
				all the expanded tags in the list will be searched and you'll jump to any 
				matching ones. 
			</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="enjoying">
		<title>Enjoying your photos</title>
		<sect1 id="enjoying-browse">
			<title>Browse</title>
			<para>
				You can use the slider widget to browse your photos by month or by 
				directory. To change this setting, go to <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Arranged By</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="enjoying-search">
			<title>Search</title>
			<para>
				You can start a search by double clicking or activating a tag from the tag 
				list. Alternatively, you can show the find bar with <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Find</guimenu><guimenuitem>Show Find Bar</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. 
				With the find bar shown, you can drag tags from the tag view to the find bar.
			</para>
			<para>
				To find photos that are tagged with both of two tags, activate the first in 
				the tag view or drag it onto the find bar, then drag the second tag and drop 
				it on top of the first. You can also right click on the second tag in the tag 
				view, or use the <guimenu>Find</guimenu> menu, and choose <guimenuitem>Find 
				With...</guimenuitem> and select the first tag (or group of tags).
			</para>
			<para>
				You can drag a tag icon around on the find bar to change from finding it and 
				another tag to finding it or another tag.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can search for photos that do not have a particular tag by double-clicking 
				on a tag in the find bar. Alternatively, you can right-click a tag in the find 
				bar and select <guimenuitem>Exclude</guimenuitem>.
			</para>
			<para>
				To remove a tag from the search, drag it away from the find bar, or right click 
				and select <guimenuitem>Remove</guimenuitem>.
			</para>
			<para>
				By default, photos tagged <emphasis>Hidden</emphasis> will not be shown. You must 
				explicitly include the <emphasis>Hidden</emphasis> tag in your search to show 
				such photos.
			</para>
			<para>
				There is also a type-to-find entry. Press <keycap>/</keycap> to open it. It cannot 
				be used at the same time as the find bar. You can type queries such as "TagA and 
				(TagB or (TagC and TagD))". At any point, if F-Spot recognizes what you've typed as 
				a valid query, it will update your search. The <emphasis>not</emphasis> operator 
				is not yet supported. 
			</para>

		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="enjoying-fullscreen-mode-and-slideshows">
			<title>Fullscreen Mode and Slideshows</title>
			<para>
				For fewer distractions and larger display, you can view your photos in full 
				screen mode. You control when to show the next photo or to return to the 
				previous. Enter fullscreen mode by pressing <keycap>F11</keycap> at 
				any time or by pressing the button in the toolbar.
			</para>
			<figure>
				<title>FullScreen</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-fullscreen.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>
				In slideshow mode, you can sit back and view your photos as they are 
				presented to you. You can start a slideshow by pressing the button on the 
				toolbar. 
			</para>
			<figure>
				<title>SlideShow</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-slideshow.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="sharing">
		<title>Sharing your photos</title>
		
		<abstract>
			<para>
				There are many ways to share your photos using F-Spot. All of the following 
				methods will only share the photos you have selected when you run them.
			</para>
		</abstract>
		
		<sect1 id="sharing-e-mail">
			<title>E-mail</title>
			<para>
				E-mail your photos directly from F-Spot with the <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Send Mail</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> menu. 
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="sharing-print">
			<title>Print</title>
			<para>
				Print your photos with the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu.
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="sharing-burn-to-cd">
			<title>Burn to CD</title>
			<para>
				
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="website-gallery-folder">
			<title>Generate a Website Gallery or Folder</title>
			<para>
				The 
				<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem>
				<guimenuitem>Export to Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice> feature 
				gives you three ways to export your images.
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Use Original</guilabel> exports your photos ready for use with 
						Jakub Steiner's free <ulink url="http://jimmac.musichall.cz/original.php">
						Original Photo Gallery</ulink> software. If you are unsure about this option, 
						it is probably not the right one for you.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Use static HTML files</guilabel> exports your photos to an 
						interactive website, ready for you to upload.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Plain Files</guilabel> exports your images as files within directories, 
						without putting them into a gallery. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="sharing-flickr-or-php-gallery">
			<title>Post to your Flickr or PHP Gallery</title>
			<para>
				If you use Flickr, you can post your files directly from F-Spot with the 
				<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem>
				<guimenuitem>Export to Flickr</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you use the PHP software known as <ulink url="http://gallery.sourceforge.net/">
				Gallery</ulink>, you can post your photos to your existing album with the 
				<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem>
				<guimenuitem>Export to Web Gallery</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu. 
				You must first enable the Remote module within your Gallery installation.
			</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="shortcuts">
		<title>Shortcuts</title>
		
		<sect1 id="Global-Shortcuts">
			<title>Global Shortcuts</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Action
							</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>[</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Rotate the selected photos to the left
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>]</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Rotate the selected photos to the right
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>t</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								View or edit tags for selected photos
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>F11</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Full screen view
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>I</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Displays information about the photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Equals</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Zoom-in
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Minus</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Zoom-out
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Import photos
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="shortcuts-browse-mode">
			<title>Browse Mode Shortcuts</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Action
							</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Select all
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap>
								<keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Unselect all
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Arrow keys (up, down, left, right) or k, j, h, l keys
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Move focus
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-arrow key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Move the focus without changing the selection
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Spacebar</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Select or unselect the focused photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
								<keycap>arrow key</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Change the photo selection
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap>
								<keycap>left arrow or right arrow</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Add/Remove all photos in the row, in the direction pressed, to the selection
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>v</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Pops up a larger preview of the picture pointed by the mouse
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>V</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Pops up a larger preview and a color histogram of the picture pointed by the mouse
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="shortcuts-tag">
			<title>Tag Shortcuts</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Action
							</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>F2</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Rename selected tag
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>T</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Add tags to selected photos
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								n/a
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Drag and drop tags to move them
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								n/a
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Type a tag's name to jump to it (only works if tag is shown/expanded)
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="shortcuts-edit-mode">
			<title>Edit Mode Shortcuts</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Action
							</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Page Up</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Go to Previous Photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Page Down</keycap>, <keycap>Spacebar</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Go to Next Photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>0</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Fit the image to the screen
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>1</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Zoom Factor to 1.0 (1 screen pixel per image pixel)
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>2</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Zoom Factor to 2.0 (4 screen pixels per image pixel)
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Escape</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Returns to Browser mode
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>v</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Examine photo with magnifying glass (Loupe)
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

</book>

