<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="f-spot" lang="C">
	<bookinfo>
		<title>The F-Spot Manual</title>
		<abstract role="description">
			<para>This is the user manual for F-Spot, a GNOME personal photo manager.</para>
		</abstract>
		<subtitle>This is the user manual for F-Spot, a GNOME personal photo manager.</subtitle>
		<copyright>
			<year>2007-2009</year>
			<holder>Aaron Bockover, Gabriel Burt, Miguel de Icaza, Bengt Thuree</holder>
		</copyright>
		<publisher>
			<publishername>GNOME Documentation Project</publishername>
		</publisher>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Miguel</firstname>
				<surname>de Icaza</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Aaron</firstname>
				<surname>Bockover</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Bengt</firstname>
				<surname>Thuree</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Gabriel</firstname>
				<surname>Burt</surname>
			</author>
			<author>
				<firstname>Alexandre</firstname>
				<surname>Prokoudine</surname>
			</author>
			<author role="maintainer">
				<firstname>Stephane</firstname>
				<surname>Delcroix</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<!--<include href="legal.xml" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>-->
		<revhistory>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>0.5</revnumber>
				<date>2008-09-25</date>
			</revision>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>0.4</revnumber>
				<date>2008-09-12</date>
			</revision>
			<revision>
				<revnumber>0.3</revnumber>
				<date>2007-07-26</date>
			</revision>
		 </revhistory>
	</bookinfo>

	<chapter id="organizing">
		<title>Organizing your photos</title>
		
		<sect1 id="import">
			<title>Import</title>

			<para>
				You can import photos from your hard drive or your camera. When you 
				import your photos into F-Spot from your camera, it will always make a 
				copy of them, leaving you free to clear your camera's memory. By default, 
				F-Spot will make a copy of photos imported from your hard drive. Uncheck 
				the <guilabel>Copy</guilabel> option on the import dialog or hold 
				<keycap>Shift</keycap> when dragging photos into F-Spot if you do not 
				wish to copy them from your hard drive.
			</para>
			
			<para>
				By default, F-Spot copies your photos to the 
				<filename class='directory'>~/Photos</filename> folder. You can change 
				the folder F-Spot uses in <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog 
				(<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>). You can also disable physical copying of images to that 
				directory and make F-Spot only reference to existing files. For that you 
				need to disable checkbox <guilabel>Copy files to the Photos folder</guilabel>. 
			</para>
			<para>
				If there is a tiny chance that some of your photos are already imported 
				from the chosen source, you can use <guilabel>Detect duplicates</guilabel> 
				option. In this case F-Spot will try to find out if exactly this image is 
				already present in the database and thus new copy of it should not be 
				imported. 
			</para>
			<para>
				If all the photos you are importing at one time are from a particular event, 
				or have some other characteristic in common, you can create a tag for them 
				so you can later find them with ease. To do this, follow the instructions from  
				<xref linkend="tag"/> to create a new tag, then when you are importing 
				them, check the button for <guilabel>Attach Tag</guilabel> and choose the 
				tag you created. 
			</para>
			
			<tip>
				<para>
					F-Spot uses a database stored at 
					<filename>~/.config/f-spot/photos.db</filename>. Note, to access it, use 
					the sqlite3 command. You can also manually specify path to a database by 
					running F-Spot with <option>-b</option> option.
				</para>
			</tip>
			
			<para>
				After an import, F-Spot will display the pictures of the latest import 
				roll only. Read <xref linkend="enjoying-search"/> to learn how to deal 
				with import rolls.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can also import directly from Mozilla 
				<ulink url="http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/firefox/">Firefox</ulink> and 
				<ulink url="http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/thunderbird/">Thunderbird</ulink> using 
				<ulink url="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/7091">Firefox</ulink> 
				and <ulink url="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/thunderbird/addon/7011">Thunderbird</ulink> 
				F-Spot importer extensions written by 
				<ulink url="http://personalpages.tds.net/~cdovel/">Pizzach</ulink>.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="edit">
			<title>Edit</title>
			
			<para>
				If you double click or press enter on an image, you enter Edit mode, where 
				you can remove red-eye, crop, and adjust brightness and colors.
			</para>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-versions">
				<title>Versions</title>
				
				<para>
					When you edit your photos, a new copy (called a version) is created, 
					so your original is never altered. After your first edit to a photo, subsequent 
					edits will modify the same version. If you want to create multiple versions 
					of your photo, perhaps with different cropping or coloring, you can do so 
					via the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Create new version</guimenuitem></menuchoice> option.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-crop">
				<title>Crop</title>
				
				<para>
					Cropping an image is a great way to improve the quality of a photograph by 
					change how it is framed. You crop a photo by selecting the part of the photo 
					you want to keep. If you want your photo to be the exact dimensions necessary 
					for a certain print size, you can constrain the kind of selection F-Spot will allow 
					you to draw by choosing the appropriate size from the constraint drop down. 
					See the <xref linkend="edit-remove-red-eye"/> below for details on making 
					a selection on your photo.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Crop tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-crop.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>
					Once you have made your crop selection, you must click the crop button beneath 
					the image to finalize the crop. If you are working with the original photo, cropping 
					creates a new version your photo.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-straighten">
				<title>Straighten</title>
				
				<para>
					Straighten effect is a tool to level a photo, quite helpful for landscapes 
					taken without a tripod, when (imaginary) line of horizon is not at 0°. 
					This tool rotates an image by a specified angle and automagically crops the 
					resulted image, so that you always see a perfect rectangle.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Straighten tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-straighten.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-adjust-colors">
				<title>Adjust Colors</title>
				
				<para>
					To adjust the brightness, contrast, and colors of a photo, first click 
					the <guibutton>Adjust the photo colors</guibutton> icon to open the 
					adjustment dialog. Change then some settings and save them with 
					<guibutton>OK</guibutton>. 
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Adjust Colors tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-adjust-colors.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-auto-color">
				<title>AutoColor</title>
				
				<para>
					This effect automatically adjusts color levels to make a pretty balanced 
					picture color-wise. It serves best for pictures taken with automatical 
					white balance, when camera didn't manage to do the job well.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>AutoColor</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-autocolor.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-desaturate">
				<title>Desaturate</title>
				
				<para>
					To make a colorful photo a black and white one, open a photo of choice 
					and press <guibutton>Desaturate</guibutton> button.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Desaturation tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-desaturate.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-sepia">
				<title>Sepia</title>
				
				<para>
					To make a colorful photo look like an old-style picture in sepia tones, 
					open a photo of choice and press <guibutton>Sepia</guibutton> button.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Desaturation tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-sepia.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-remove-red-eye">
				<title>Remove Red-Eye</title>
				
				<para>
					To remove redeye from a photo, you need to select a zone containing 
					the eyes. You may want to zoom in on the image to accurately select 
					the eyes in the photo. You should be able to correct both eyes on the 
					same person in one shot, or even the eyes from multiple people at once. 
					If this doesn't work for you, or the selected zone contains some vivid 
					red parts (lips, ...) you'll probably have to correct one red eye at a time.
				</para>
				<para>
					To make your selection, click one corner of the rectangle that will be your 
					selection, and drag your mouse to the diagonal corner and release it. You 
					can resize your selection by dragging its edges, and you can move it by 
					clicking in the middle of it and dragging it to where you want it.
				</para>
				<para>
					Once you have selected a zone, you can remove the red from it by 
					clicking the red-eye button beneath the photo.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Red-Eye tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-red-eye.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<tip>
					<para>
						You can change the threshold for redeyes detection by changing 
						the gconf key 
						<filename class='directory'>/apps/f-spot/edit/redeye_threshold</filename>.
					</para>
				</tip>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-soft-focus">
				<title>Soft Focus</title>
				
				<para>
					In photography sharpening one region of a picture, while blurring 
					all the rest, is a way to make an emphasis and grab attention. 
					It is achieved by using a lens that allows shooting with a short 
					distance in front of and beyond the subject that appears to be in 
					focus. Soft focus effect is a way to emulate such a lens.
				</para>
				<figure>
					<title>Soft Focus tool</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-soft-focus.png"/>
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</figure>
				<para>
					Click to choose central point of the area you want to be in focus 
					and adjust amount of blurring, then click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-sharpen">
				<title>Sharpen</title>
				
				<para>
					Out-of-focus photographs and most digitized images often need a 
					sharpness correction. The Unsharp Mask effect sharpens edges of 
					the elements without increasing noise or blemish. To sharpen a 
					photo choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Sharpen...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and specify the 
					following values:
				</para>
				
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class='option'>Amount</parameter> — strength of sharpening.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class='option'>Radius</parameter> — how many pixels on either 
							side of an edge will be affected by sharpening. High resolution images 
							allow higher radius.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class='option'>Threshold</parameter> — the minimum difference 
							in pixel values that indicates an edge where sharpen must be applied. 
							This helps avoiding creation of blemishes in face, sky or water surface.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="edit-describe">
				<title>Describe</title>
				
				<para>
					You can also enter a description of the image by clicking on the text entry box 
					below the image and typing. 
				</para>
				<para>
					Once you have made your crop selection, you must click the crop button beneath 
					the image to finalize the crop. If you are working with the original photo, cropping 
					creates a new version your photo.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="edit-adjust-time">
				<title>Adjust Time</title>
				
				<para>
					In both 'browse' or 'edit' modes, you can adjust the time of one 
					or multiple pictures (<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
					<guimenuitem>Adjust Time</guimenuitem></menuchoice>). Adjusting 
					the time of multiple pictures at once helps you shift all an import 
					roll if, e.g. the time on your camera is badly set or if you forgot 
					to change it according to DST.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="tag">
			<title>Tag</title>
			<para>
				F-Spot enables you to organize and enjoy your photos by associating them 
				with various user-customizable tags. A tag is a merely a label. F-Spot comes 
				with default tags to get you started; you are free to change them and 
				add new ones. For example, if you want to create a tag for specific event, you 
				can create a new tag named after that event under the Events tag.
			</para>
			<para>
				There are many ways to tag photos:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						drag and drop the photo(s) onto the tag
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						drag and drop the tag onto the photo(s)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						via the photo's right-click menu
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						via the Tags and Edit menus
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						by typing them in. Press <keycap>t</keycap> to pop up the tag
						entry bar. Here you can enter the tags, separated by commas.
					</para>
					<para>
						You can also use auto-completion in this entry bar: After
						entering the beginning of a tag name, press
						<keycap>Tab</keycap> to see the first possible completion. You can
						cycle between other possible completions by pressing
						<keycap>Tab</keycap> again, and backwards with
						<keycombo action="simul"><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>.
						To confirm the suggested completion and enter a new tag, press
						<keycap>,</keycap>. By pressing <keycap>Enter</keycap> you
						leave the tag entry bar, possibly confirming the current
						completion. To abort the auto completion, just keep on typing.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				The first photo you associate with a tag will be used for that tag's icon. 
				You can always edit a tag's name, parent tag, and icon by right clicking 
				on it and choosing <guilabel>Edit tag</guilabel>.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can change a tag's parent by dragging and dropping it where you like. 
				Also, you can edit the name of a tag by selecting it and pressing 
				<keycap>F2</keycap>. Lastly, if you have the tag tree widget focused 
				(e.g. you just clicked on a tag), you can start typing the name of a tag, and 
				all the expanded tags in the list will be searched and you'll jump to any 
				matching ones. 
			</para>
			
			<para>
				You can also change size of tag icons in the sidebar or even make tag 
				icons invisible by selecting preferred option from <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Tag Icons</guimenuitem></menuchoice> 
				menu.
			</para>
			
			<tip>
				<para>
					F-Spot can write tags as metadata fields into JPEG files. Tags for 
					various RAW files, PNG, TIFF, and others are written to F-Spot's 
					database. You will have to re-tag these files if you re-import your 
					collection.
				</para>
			</tip>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="enjoying">
		<title>Enjoying your photos</title>
		<sect1 id="enjoying-browse">
			<title>Browse</title>
			<para>
				You can use the slider widget to browse your photos by month or by 
				directory. To change this setting, go to <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Arranged By</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
			</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="enjoying-search">
			<title>Search</title>
			
			<para>
				F-Spot uses search filters to help you better define search criteria.
			</para>
			
			<sect2 id="enjoying-search-tags">
				<title>Tags</title>
				
				<para>
					You can start a search by double clicking or activating a tag from 
					the tag list. Alternatively, you can show the find bar with <menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Find</guimenu><guimenuitem>Show Find Bar</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. 
					With the find bar shown, you can drag tags from the tag view to the find bar.
				</para>
				<para>
					To find photos that are tagged with both of two tags, activate the first in 
					the tag view or drag it onto the find bar, then drag the second tag and drop 
					it on top of the first. You can also right click on the second tag in the tag 
					view, or use the <guimenu>Find</guimenu> menu, and choose <guimenuitem>Find 
					With...</guimenuitem> and select the first tag (or group of tags).
				</para>
				<para>
					You can drag a tag icon around on the find bar to change from finding it and 
					another tag to finding it or another tag.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can search for photos that do not have a particular tag by double-clicking 
					on a tag in the find bar. Alternatively, you can right-click a tag in the find 
					bar and select <guimenuitem>Exclude</guimenuitem>.
				</para>
				<para>
					To remove a tag from the search, drag it away from the find bar, or right click 
					and select <guimenuitem>Remove</guimenuitem>.
				</para>
				<para>
					By default, photos tagged <emphasis>Hidden</emphasis> will not be shown. You must 
					explicitly include the <emphasis>Hidden</emphasis> tag in your search to show 
					such photos.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="enjoying-search-import-rolls">
				<title>Import Rolls</title>
				<para>
					F-Spot remembers what pictures were imported every now and then. Use 
					<menuchoice><guimenu>Find</guimenu><guisubmenu>Import Roll</guisubmenu>
					<guimenuitem>Last import roll</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to limit search 
					to last importing session or use <menuchoice><guimenu>Find</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Import Roll</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Select Import Rolls...</guimenuitem>
					</menuchoice> to make a finer selection of imported photos:
				</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class='option'>At</parameter> — to select photos from a particular importing session
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class='option'>After</parameter> — to select all photos imported begining with a particular importing session
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<parameter class='option'>Between</parameter> — to select all photos imported between two particular importing sessions
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>
					Every time you change settings of the filter, the amount of selected photos 
					will appear in the bottom part of the dialog.
				</para>
				<para>
					When you apply Import Roll filter, in the Find bar you will see 
					<guilabel>Find: Import Roll</guilabel>. Now you can add some other 
					filter to finetune your selection.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you don't need the Import Roll filter anymore, choose <menuchoice>
					<guimenu>Find</guimenu><guisubmenu>Import Roll</guisubmenu>
					<guimenuitem>Clear roll filter</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to remove 
					Import Roll from search criteria. You can also click the close button 
					(<guibutton>X</guibutton>) of the search bar to discard all the current 
					search options.
				</para>
				<tip>
					<para>
						The number of displayed rolls in the dialog is defined by the gconf key 
						<filename class='directory'>/apps/f-spot/import/gui_roll_history</filename>. 
						Default value is 10.
					</para>
				</tip>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="enjoying-search-type-to-find">
				<title>Type-to-find</title>
				<para>
					There is also a type-to-find entry. Press <keycap>/</keycap> to open it. It cannot 
					be used at the same time as the find bar. You can type queries such as "TagA and 
					(TagB or (TagC and TagD))". At any point, if F-Spot recognizes what you've typed as 
					a valid query, it will update your search. The <emphasis>not</emphasis> operator 
					is not yet supported. 
				</para>
				
				<para>
					This function will also search for the typed text into photos comments and filename.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="enjoying-fullscreen-mode-and-slideshows">
			<title>Fullscreen Mode and Slideshows</title>
			<para>
				For fewer distractions and larger display, you can view your photos in full 
				screen mode. You control when to show the next photo or to return to the 
				previous. Enter fullscreen mode by pressing <keycap>F11</keycap> at 
				any time or by pressing the button in the toolbar.
			</para>
			<figure>
				<title>FullScreen</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-fullscreen.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			<para>
				In slideshow mode, you can sit back and view your photos as they are 
				presented to you. You can start a slideshow by pressing the button on the 
				toolbar. 
			</para>
			<figure>
				<title>SlideShow</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="figures/f-spot-slideshow.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="sharing">
		<title>Sharing your photos</title>
		
		<abstract>
			<para>
				There are many ways to share your photos using F-Spot. All of the following 
				methods will only share the photos you have selected when you run them.
			</para>
		</abstract>
		
		<sect1 id="sharing-e-mail">
			<title>E-mail</title>
			<para>
				E-mail your photos directly from F-Spot with the <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Send Mail</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> menu. 
			</para>
			<note>
				<title>Note 1</title>
				<para>
					The email program used for this is defined at the GNOME level. 
					You can change the default e-mailer for your user using the 
					<application>Preferred Applications</application> tool in 
					<menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu>
					<guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu></menuchoice>.
				</para>
			</note>
			<note>
				<title>Note 2</title>
				<para>
					If some of the photos you'd like to send by email are in a format 
					that F-Spot can't write (e.g. RAW images), the size selection dialog 
					will become insensitive and the originals will be sent.
				</para>
			</note>
			<tip>
				<para>
					If you're sending resized pictures, F-Spot will keep the modified versions 
					somewhere in the <filename class='directory'>/tmp</filename> directory for 
					30 seconds. It's not an issue with evolution, which makes it's own local 
					copy of the attachments, but could be a bit shorter if you're using Thunderbird. 
					You can change the delay by editing the gconf key 
					<filename class='directory'>/apps/f-spot/export/email/delete_timeout_seconds</filename>.
				</para>
			</tip>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="sharing-print">
			<title>Print</title>
			<para>
				Print your photos with the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu.
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="sharing-burn-to-cd">
			<title>Burn to CD</title>
			<para>
				Burn your photos to CD or DVD with the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
				<guisubmenu>Export</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Export to CD</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice> menu.
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="website-gallery-folder">
			<title>Generate a Website Gallery or Folder</title>
			<para>
				The 
				<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem>
				<guimenuitem>Export to Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice> feature 
				gives you three ways to export your images.
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Use Original</guilabel> exports your photos ready for use with 
						Jakub Steiner's free <ulink url="http://jimmac.musichall.cz/original.php">
						Original Photo Gallery</ulink> software. If you are unsure about this option, 
						it is probably not the right one for you.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Use static HTML files</guilabel> exports your photos to an 
						interactive website, ready for you to upload.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<guilabel>Plain Files</guilabel> exports your images as files within directories, 
						without putting them into a gallery. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="sharing-flickr-or-php-gallery">
			<title>Post to your online galleries</title>
			<para>
				If you use Flickr, SmugMug, 23hq, Tabblo, Facebook, Zooomr or Picasa Web Album, you can post your files 
				directly from F-Spot with the <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu>
				<guisubmenu>Export</guisubmenu></menuchoice> menu, choosing corresponding submenu item.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you use the PHP software known as <ulink url="http://gallery.sourceforge.net/">
				Gallery</ulink>, you can post your photos to your existing album with the 
				<menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Export</guimenuitem>
				<guimenuitem>Export to Web Gallery</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu. 
				You must first enable the Remote module within your Gallery installation.
			</para>
			<note>
				<title>Note for Gallery 2.2 users</title>
				<para>
					The Remote plugin for Gallery should be 1.0.8 or newer.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				<ulink url="http://pennave.sourceforge.net">PennAve</ulink> is a Python 
				web-application that directly uses F-Spot's database to present a dynamic 
				gallery of your photos and tags.
			</para>
			<para>
				<ulink url="http://www.conduit-project.org">Conduit</ulink> is an application 
				that can sync photos that have a particular tag with your Flickr or Picasa 
				Web Album web storage.
			</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

	<chapter id="cms">
		<title>Color management</title>

		<sect1 id="cms-what-is-cms">
			<title>What's color management</title>
			
			<para>
				When you capture a photo and look at it on a display, it looks different than 
				on a camera's preview display or on any other display. It will also look 
				different when you print it. This is because every device has unique color 
				reproduction capabilities.
			</para>

			<para>
				Color management system (CMS) is a tool to achieve reliable color reproduction 
				for both display and output (e.g. a printer). A CMS relies on color profiles 
				to map original colors to the color that a device can reproduce so that colors 
				will appear the same way everywhere — on a computer LCD monitor, on a print 
				from your local photolab etc.
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="cms-what-is-icc-profile">
			<title>What's a color profile</title>
			
			<para>
				A color profile is a file with either .icc (thus its is often called an ICC 
				profile) or .icm extension that describes how device's colors correspond to a 
				universal description of colors.
			</para>

			<para>
				There are several types of profiles: 
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Input device profile. It's profile for a camera or a profile that an 
						application like XSane embeds into a scanned image. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Working space profile. It's a profile that describes color space in 
						which all operations are done inside an application. Usually very wide 
						gamut profiles like AdobeRGB1998 or ProPhotoRGB are used for that.
					</para>				
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Display profile. It's a profile for a monitor. 
					</para>				
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Output profile. This is usually a profile for you printer. 
					</para>				
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>					

			<para>
				Currently F-Spot allows setting only display and output profiles. 
				All color operations are done in sRGB color space. 
			</para>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="cms-how-to-get-icc-profile">
			<title>How to get my screen/printer color profile </title>

			<para>
				There are few ways to get a color profile. 
			</para>
			
			<sect2 id="cms-icc-from-cd-or-internet">
				<title> From CD or Internet </title>

				<para>
					Many hardware manufacturers put color profiles into CD in the bundle. 
					If you have one (from monitor or printer), you can use it. Or you can 
					download it from the Internet (usually, from support section of the 
					manufacturer's web site). Some camera manufacturers (Nikon, Canon) 
					also provide ICC profiles.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="cms-icc-from-calibrating-and-profiling">
				<title>Calibrating and profiling</title>

				<para>
					Best results can be achieved by calibrating and profiling devices with 
					a measurement device. It is not so difficult, but it means that you need 
					a spectrophotometer to do all measurements and create an ICC profile.
				</para>

				<para>
					If you are on Windows or Mac OS X, you can use manufacturer's software 
					coming with a spectrophotometer. On Linux you will have to use either 
					<ulink url="http://www.argyllcms.com">Argyll</ulink>, which is a set of 
					versatile command line tools, or 
					<ulink url="http://lprof.sourceforge.net/">LProf</ulink>, which has a 
					graphical user interface. 
				</para>
				<para>
					Please refer to documentation of third party hardware and software 
					vendors for details.
				</para>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="cms-icc-from-embedding">
				<title>Embedding</title>

				<para>
					Image formats themselves (such as TIFF, JPEG, PNG...) may contain embedded 
					color profiles. If color management is enabled, F-Spot looks for such 
					embedded profiles and takes them into consideration.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="cms-how-to-use">
			<title>How to use color management in F-Spot</title>
			
			<para>
				Color management in F-Spot can use only RGB profiles at this time 
				(and you can't see other profiles in the F-Spot).
			</para>

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Copy your color profiles into the 
						<filename class='directory'>/usr/share/color/icc</filename> or 
						<filename class='directory'>/usr/local/share./color/icc</filename> 
						directory.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Enable the color management with the <menuchoice>
						<guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice> menu.
					</para>				
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Select <guilabel>Display</guilabel> and <guilabel>Output</guilabel> 
						profiles.
					</para>				
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>					

			<tip>
				<para>
					You can use <ulink url="http://burtonini.com/blog/computers/xicc">xicc</ulink> 
					to load ICC profile to display and use the loaded profile from F-Spot. 
					Just mark the checkbox <guilabel>Try to use the system display 
					profile</guilabel>.
				</para>
			</tip>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="extend">
		<title>Extend functionality</title>
		
		<sect1 id="extend-what-extensions-are">
			<title>What extensions are</title>

			<para>
				F-Spot extensions are means to add new functionality to the application. 
				F-Spot supports two types of extension: exporters (which allow exporting 
				photos to new web services or data storages) and tools (which allow new 
				ways of color correction, duplicate photos finders etc.). Extensions are 
				distributed in form of extension packages.
			</para>
			<para>
				In the best traditions of not reinventing the wheel extensions can use other 
				extensions, which means that one extension cannot work, if another extension 
				is not installed. This concept of dependance actually means that
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						you cannot install an extension, if the extension it depends on, is not present in the system
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						you cannot remove an extension on which some other extension depends
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="extend-managing-extensions">
			<title>Managing extensions</title>
			
			<para>
				To manage extensions choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Manage Extensions</guimenuitem></menuchoice> menu item.
			</para>

			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-managing-extension-repositories">
				<title>Managing extension repositories</title>

				<para>
					Simply put, repositories are extension storages. They can be either network 
					or local. To add a new repository click Repositories button, choose type of 
					the repository you are about to add and provide either URL or path. If the URL 
					or path you specified doesn't contain a description (index) file for extensions, 
					a warning message will pop up to tell you that.
				</para>
				<para>
					To remove a repository click <guibutton>Repositories</guibutton> button again, 
					choose the repository you are about to delete and click 
					<guibutton>Delete</guibutton> button.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-installing-and-updating-extensions">
				<title>Installing and updating extensions</title>

				<para>
					To install an extension click <guibutton>Install extensions...</guibutton> button. 
					In the newly presented dialog
				</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Choose repository to install from all known repositories or just one of 
							available repositories.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Choose, what extension packages you want to see: All, Only new, Only updates.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click the <guibutton>Update</guibutton> button to update list of available 
							extension packages by given criteria.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Choose extensions you want to install/update, click <guibutton>Information</guibutton> 
							to see summary on selected package, if you want to.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Click <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> to proceed with installation.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-enabling-and-disabling-extensions">
				<title>Enabling and disabling extensions</title>

				<para>
					You might want to temporarily enable or disable a particular extension package, 
					for example, if the extension is not stable enough to handle a large amount of 
					photos or if menus get crowded with extensions.
				</para>
				<para>
					In the <guilabel>Manage Extensions</guilabel> dialog select the extension 
					package and click <guibutton>Enable</guibutton> or <guibutton>Disable</guibutton>. 
				</para>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-removing-extensions">
				<title>Removing extensions</title>

				<para>
					If you don't need an extension you can remove it from the system completely. 
					In the <guilabel>Manage Extensions</guilabel> dialog select the extension 
					package you want to remove and click <guibutton>Delete</guibutton>.
				</para>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="extend-managing-extensions-reading-summary-of-extensions">
				<title>Reading summary of extensions</title>

				<para>
					Every extension package contains metadata that provides the following information about the extension:
				</para>

				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Description, which usually covers puprose of the extension
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Version
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Author
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Dependencies
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
				
				<para>
					In the <guilabel>Manage Extensions</guilabel> dialog select the extension 
					package you want to read summary of and click <guibutton>Information</guibutton>.
				</para>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="extend-developing-extensions">
			<title>Developing extensions</title>

			<para>
				<ulink url="http://f-spot.org/Extend_F-Spot">Extend F-Spot</ulink> document 
				gives instructions on developing your own extensions for F-Spot.
			</para>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter id="shortcuts">
		<title>Shortcuts</title>
		
		<sect1 id="Global-Shortcuts">
			<title>Global Shortcuts</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Action
							</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>[</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Rotate the selected photos to the left
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>]</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Rotate the selected photos to the right
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Del</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Remove selected photos from F-Spot's catalogue
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Del</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Delete selected photos permanently from the drive. If possible, they will moved to trash.
							</entry>
						</row>
 
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>t</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								View or edit tags for selected photos
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>F11</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Full screen view
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>I</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Displays information about the photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Equals</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Zoom-in
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Minus</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Zoom-out
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Import photos
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>0-5</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Alt plus a number from 0 to 5 rate the selected picture(s)
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="shortcuts-browse-mode">
			<title>Browse Mode Shortcuts</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Action
							</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Select all
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap>
								<keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Unselect all
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Arrow keys or <keycap>H</keycap>, <keycap>J</keycap>, 
								<keycap>K</keycap>, <keycap>L</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Move focus
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-Arrow key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Move the focus without changing the selection
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Spacebar</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Select or unselect the focused photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
								<keycap>Arrow key</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Change the photo selection
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap>
								<keycap>Left arrow or Right arrow</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Add/Remove all photos in the row, in the direction pressed, to the selection
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>V</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Pops up a larger preview of the picture pointed by the mouse
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>V</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Pops up a larger preview and a color histogram of the picture pointed by the mouse
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="shortcuts-tag">
			<title>Tag Shortcuts</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Action
							</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>F2</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Rename selected tag
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>T</keycap></keycombo>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Add tags to selected photos
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								n/a
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Drag and drop tags to move them
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								n/a
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Type a tag's name to jump to it (only works if tag is shown/expanded)
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="shortcuts-edit-mode">
			<title>Edit Mode Shortcuts</title>
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Key
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Action
							</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Page Up</keycap>, <keycap>Backspace</keycap>, <keycap>B</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Go to Previous Photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Page Down</keycap>, <keycap>Spacebar</keycap>, <keycap>N</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Go to Next Photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								Arrow keys or <keycap>H</keycap>, <keycap>J</keycap>, 
								<keycap>K</keycap>, <keycap>L</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Go to Previous/Next photo or move around a zoomed photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>R</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Go to a random photo
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>f</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Full screen view
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>0</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Fit the image to the screen
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>1</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Zoom Factor to 1.0 (1 screen pixel per image pixel)
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>2</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Zoom Factor to 2.0 (4 screen pixels per image pixel)
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Escape</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Returns to Browser mode
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>V</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Examine photo with magnifying glass (Loupe). Doubleclick on the 
								Loupe, or type <keycap>v</keycap> again to close it.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>Shift</keycap>-Mousewheel
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Faster filmstrip scrolling
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>
								<keycap>i</keycap>
							</entry>
							<entry>
								Toggle infobox visibility ''(only when in full screen)''
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
		</sect1>
	</chapter>

</book>

